but first you know why are they actually
search I'd really stated plus it synced
Lee is that time the advancing threats
to humanity outpace the intensity scale
a behavioral response so what do I mean
by that what I mean is that we have
melting ice sheets in the Arctic we have
a destabilized financial system that's
causing widespread hardship all right we
have natural disasters flooding tsunamis
earthquakes volcanoes tornadoes all
these things that are happening around
us that are making it hard for us to
live our lives then we have these really
weird problems of abundance and scarcity
some people have incredible wealth and
yet so many people don't have enough and
at the same time we're in the midst we
paid where we no longer have an
abundance of natural resources we're
running out of oil we're running out of
precious metals we're running out of
potable water and so so in this period
we're all these really big things is
kind of cluster of threats that created
this huge existential quandary for
humanity and our behavioral response is
not happening big enough or fast enough
to respond to that change and that's why
we're here today is to start to really
address that big picture so to help give
this a little bit of a temporal context
let's let's look this is mostly us
cultural history but I think it maps
onto the world fairly wells there was
this time back in the 60s when it seemed
like things might be going a little
differently there was a lot of awakening
of consciousness for people they were
talking about peace instead of war
bringing down Empire they were talking
about love and compassion and then we
had you know some people in our
political space some leaders who were
starting to advance a more progressive
notion of the world that young e EPA was
created we have these institutions
starting to get set up looks like we
might be making progress and then
what happened then we had this turnover
where the culture started to shift in a
different direction and we starting to
have people who were opposed very
structurally strategically almost
militaristic alee opposed to this kind
of a shift in the culture and they
reversed it in some ways they took us to
another place and we had this
progression of political leaders and
business leaders who are taking us
somewhere other than addressing the deep
threats that that sixties generation was
really starting to shed light on and
yell and that's led us to a point where
now we have this huge pics of problems
and we're not responding to them on the
appropriate scale and you know sure we
have this networked world that is being
created there create some new
possibilities for us but we haven't
unleashed the power and potential of a
creativity to turn the culture back in
the right direction again and I think
there are a lot of things moving us in
that direction but that's what we're
trying to do is in our conversation
today is talk about how do we get that
big cultural shift consciousness shift
realignment of norms and values
so what didn't we see when we started
this March at toward progress 50 years
ago but we didn't see the
corporatization of America we didn't see
how powerful that would be we didn't see
that there would be these incredibly
powerful propaganda communication
systems I would set a specific agenda
and largely influenced the way people
see the world then we didn't see
astroturf thing and sophisticated ways
of engaging people around real concerns
with fictitious threats to mobilize them
against change all of that has happened
and there's something else we didn't see
because we didn't see this tremendous
investment in an infrastructure for
opposing what we're trying to do now
this network map right here shows
basically two colors the blue is all of
the liberal think tanks in the United
States and the red is all the
conservative think tanks in the United
States as of a few years ago in 2006 is
when they made this so what this shows
is that over the last 40 to 50 years
there has been a strategic substantive
very large investment in a communication
system that is directly opposed to us
that is directly opposed to equality
fairness justice sustainability and so
it's not that you know we just were men
of moving along and we made some
mistakes we actually had some forces
pushing very strongly against us and
we're going to have to be able to push
back against them effectively as we move
forward so this gets back to that big
question how do we design for
large-scale change it turns out the
ancient mystics and the wisdom of the
ages has an answer for us the answer
lies within turns out they were right
that's true the answer lies within by
which I mean that if we understand what
it means to be human we can use that
understanding to design change processes
that actually appeal to humans and then
help create change that creates thriving
in human community so if we look within
ourselves we can reveal that blind spot
we can see what's there and then we can
design for change more effectively so
one of the big problems that we've had
in designing for change is that we've
had this what I call an assumed human
nature which is this idea that we're
calculating machines who weigh the pros
and cons and every choice try and get
the maximal outcome just like we're
calculators now this is a nice theory
for mathematicians looking at economics
back in the 1940s but I like to call the
assumed theory of human nature because
it's not really how we work the way the
human beings work is something a little
different so really exciting thing and
this is something that inspires me a lot
is for the first time ever in human
history we now are starting to really
understand what human nature is so in
the last 40 years there's been a
revolution happening in academia
studying how the mind works and what
human nature is it comes from fields
like evolutionary psychology we're
neuroscience or linguistics this huge
body of knowledge that's been developed
this telling us a different view of a
human nature is and its scientific which
means that we have methods for
critiquing improving falsifying so we
know whether we're right or not and so
this is something that's been developing
for quite some time but it's not really
trickled its way into society yet it's
starting to but that's a really
inspiring and hopeful idea that we
actually have started to really
understand what it means to be human
quite an accomplishment for us so what
we're learning about what it means to be
human is what's sometimes called the
embodied mind and the embodied mind is a
notion that the way that human beings
work is partially a matter of our
ecological history or physical and
biological nature the cultural as well
as both environments around us that all
shape who we are and how we work so I
like to think of it as the kinds of
brains we have the kinds of bodies we
have and the kinds of environments we
find ourselves in both physical and
cultural shape the kinds of minds that
we have at the same time we've learned
things like we're wired for empathy that
we have really powerful ways of
believing things about the world rather
than simply reasoning about them but at
the same time we haven't
credible capacity for reason and logic
so we have this these aspects of who we
are that are really interesting there
are a lot more than just being a
calculator for us to have a tribal
nature of this way of wanting to be in
group with others so these things that
we're learning about how we work and
there I think of them as kind of
liberating they're empowering if we
understand what it means to be tribal
yes that can be divisive and make people
into different groups but it can also
mean that we can be inclusive and we can
work together and collaborate so it's
part of who we are so Scott idea of
embodiment is really important and
everything that we talked about today of
regarding the mind it's important to
keep in mind that we can ground it back
in our brains and our bodies and our
communities it's not just this abstract
the mind is out there doing its thing
it's embedded its ecological
so that's pretty cool and and to give
you a sense of what I mean let's go
through a couple examples of some things
that we've been learning about the mind
and I don't know if you've ever gotten
this email I loved it when I first got
it but you know if you can read English
you can make sense of this paragraph
even though the letters within the words
are all mixed up and it sells is
something really important about how our
minds work it tells us that our minds
are set up to see patterns in the world
that are familiar to us and to fill in
information in a way that helps us to
understand what's happening in those
situations so my ability to process
language lets me see the kind of Gestalt
or the bigger pattern of the sentence
structure through the word the words in
the spacing in the words and then I'm
able to make sense of it and my brain is
filling in that information for me and I
kind of get it for free I don't have to
do any act of work my brain just does it
so our brains do this pattern matching
process just really useful to know about
another one you know i should say i love
animals i really love elephants and i
especially love levitating elephants if
you look at this optical illusion you'll
see that the legs actually don't connect
to the body and and yours it's kind of a
fun little thing but one of the things
this tells us is that our brains don't
just do pattern matching they also do
pattern completion they will fill in
patterns but they don't just fill them
in in any old way they fill them in in a
way that makes things meaningful they
create these Gestalt understandings so
when you're looking at the top of the
elephant your brain is trying to make
the legs attached when you're looking at
the bottom of the elephant it's trying
to shift the body over onto the legs so
your brain is completing the information
for you in ways that are meaningful and
useful and so it's it's not just that we
see the world as it is we see the world
as it is meaningful to us and that our
brains just do this for us which is
pretty cool now this is another one you
might have seen you know if you look at
the black part it looks like a vase if
you look at the white part it looks like
faces this actually tells us something
incredibly important about how our
brains work
this is phenomenon called mutual
inhibition what that is is when your
brain is creating a pattern which is you
know the neurons are firing into this
pattern structure which is the
information that represents the idea
when it's forming that pattern if
there's a different pattern that
contradicts it that makes it confusing
there's a part of your brain that shuts
down those circuits that's called mutual
inhibition for one circuit to be active
the other must be inhibited now to
really understand this with example
think about what happens when a person
is having an epileptic seizure their
brain is just having random firing all
over the place and what it does it shuts
down consciousness and they pass out so
I tells us is that our brains need to
have the ability to regulate themselves
to create coherence and to do that they
have to inhabit one idea to create
another cognitive dissonance is um I
would maybe there's a higher level
phenomenon that includes this for there
to be cognitive dissonance you have to
have two ideas that are kind of battling
it out for which one is going to get
dominance but that process of mutual in
addition is why that happens and I think
it's helpful to think about it from an
information processing perspective
because then you can understand why is
there dissonance those dissonance
because for this to make sense and this
to be there at the same time that
doesn't work so if this is different
from that I have to suppress one to have
the other one be active that's the
information processing point